Experience the Holiday Classic as You've Never Seen it Before
The Nutcracker is a music, fantasy, family film directed by Andrei Konchalovsky.
In 1920s Vienna, a young girl receives a magical doll on Christmas Eve.
Mary, played by Elle Fanning.
Uncle Albert, played by Nathan Lane.
The Rat King, played by John Turturro.
The Rat Queen / Frau Eva, played by Frances de la Tour.
The Prince / Nicholas Charles, played by Charlie Rowe.
Max, played by Aaron Michael Drozin.
The Nutcracker in 3D (also released as The Nutcracker: The Untold Story) is a 2010 3D Christmas
musical fantasy film adapted from Pyotr Ilyich Tchaikovsky's 1892 ballet The Nutcracker.
Directed, co-written and produced by Andrei Konchalovsky, the film stars Elle
Fanning, Nathan Lane, John Turturro, Frances de la Tour, Richard E.
Grant and Yulia Vysotskaya, with Charlie Rowe and
Shirley Henderson as the Nutcracker.
Set in 1920s Vienna, the plot follows a young girl who receives a magical doll that is revealed
to be a prince and embarks on an adventure to save his kingdom from the Rat King.
The film was an international co-production of the
United Kingdom, Russia and Hungary.
It was released on November 24, 2010 in the United States and Canada,
with later releases in Hungary and the United Kingdom.
The film was a major critical and commercial failure, becoming one of 41 films to garner
a 0% rating on Rotten Tomatoes with over 32 reviews as of October 2025.
The film was widely panned for its story, visuals, deviations from the ballet, and the
decision to adapt Tchaikovsky's score into lyrical musical numbers.
The film also received criticism for its allusions to World War II and
the Holocaust, and making the Rats reminiscent of Nazis.
It bombed at the box-office, grossing $20 million against a $90 million budget.
The film explores themes of nazi, fairy, musical,
based on play or musical, ballet.